Mary Chrystie Papers, 1833-1841: Finding Aid
Cotsen Children's Library
- Correspondence, 1833-1841; 1830s-1840s; 15.0 folders (Box 1)
  - Prayers, Poems, and Miscellaneous Notes Written by Mary Chrystie, 1833-1872; 11.0 items
    - Note by Frances Chrystie on a prayer by Mary Chrystie, Undated; 4.0 pages 18.5 x 22.6 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      No date, but after Mary Chrystie's death in 1842. A note written by Mary's mother, Frances Chrystie, explaining how she found the above described prayer ("Prayer of Dedication") written by Mary; Frances Chrystie found the prayer in 1836 but did not tell Mary that she had discovered it until "a few days before she left us." Mrs. Chrystie goes on to relate how she told Mary it was apparent that she had dedicated herself to God at a very young age. She then explains that Mary responded by saying "I was very wicked." Mrs. Chrystie recalls that at the time the prayer was written Mary was constantly questioning how her mother knew whether everything the Bible said was true. Mrs. Chrystie concludes: "I think when I mentioned the enclosed paper it awakened regret at her sceptical feelings that winter and the way in which she often expressed them to me."
    - Prayer: "O Lord help me...", Undated; 4.0 pages 13.5 x 18.4 cm One piece of ruled paper. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      No date. "Oh Lord help me prays (sic) and all my friends all the days of our youth to serve you and love you. Amen for Jesus Christ sake even so Amen. Oh lord make every body on earth love and serve thee, give them new hearts and holy minds."
    - Poem: "Afraid", 1872 May 23; 4.0 pages 18 x 24.7 cm On pattern-printed sheet folded in half. Indecipherable watermark. Second leaf torn in half but all present. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Poem in an unknown hand entitled "Afraid" by Laura Redden Searing, pseudonym Howard Glyndon. 5 stanzas of 4 lines (aabb). The following date is written after the poem in pencil and in a different hand: "May 23rd 1872." This poem was first published on February 24, 1872 in Appleton's Journal Volume 7, Issue 152 (see Sweet Bells Jangled ed. Judy Yaeger Jones and Jane E. Vallier).
    - Two Poems: "The Crucifixion" and Untitled, Undated; 4.0 pages 19.7 x 32.2 cm One ruled sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      The first poem, copied by Mary Chrystie(?) through stanza 9, is "The Crucifixion," originally published in The Amulet for 1830, and later reprinted in religious periodicals including The Evangelical Magazine and Missionary Chronicle, Volume 7. The scond poem, verso, appears to be an original composition by Mary Chrystie. It is an unfinished, untitled poem of two 4-line stanzas, with third stanza marker present but no text. It contrasts the happiness of children at "mery" (sic) harvest time ("Very joyous is their joys") with the feelings of "a little child thats sick" who wishes to "run through snow and the rain."
    - Hymn: "I Heard the Voice of Jesus Say", Undated; 3.0 pages Hymn: 20.5 x 25.4 cm. Letter: 20.4 x 26.7 cm. Hymn: One ruled sheet folded in half. Letter: One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      A copy in an unknown hand of the Horatius Bonar Hymn "I Heard the Voice of Jesus Say" (included in his Hymns, Original and Selected, 1846). Originally enclosed in a later envelope with a brief note, undated save for "27 March Saturday," and signed by a Mr. Plats (?): "I enclose you a letter received this morning from Mr. Buckley--I suppose he will be back here by next week Saturday."
    - Envelope for previous item, Undated; 1.0 item 13.9 x 17.9 cm One unmarked envelope. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Unmarked envelope in which the above items were enclosed (Hymn "I Heard the Voice of Jesus Say" and Note).
    - Fragment: Description of a Horse, Undated; 1.0 pages 6.6 x 12.4 cm Fragment of ruled paper. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      An incomplete note, presumably by Mary Chrystie, describing a horse she has raised and seems to be selling: "...untill a few week past she has never been handled untill short time past Rode but a few times and only few miles at a time quite gentle and kind with fine action. I Think to take her fine size beauty action temper & Blood she is the finest horse I ever raised She is full 3/4 Therough (sic) Bred If from the above description she should suit/ turnover..." Here the page ends.
    - Fragment: Two Sketches, Undated; 2.0 pages 9.8 x 12.2 cm One sheet with vertical crease. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      A fragment or perhaps an enclosure from one of Mary Chrystie's letters. Recto: the note "I will write you a few words and draw you another picture," with a pencil sketch of a small house and trees. Verso: "Continued. As I told you in my last letter about the picture I will draw it in this piece of letter," with a pencil sketch of a street or farmyard(?).
    - Fragment of a Journal, Undated; 4.0 pages 19.3 x 31.6 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      An aborted attempt(?) by Mary Chrystie to start a journal. The text, headed with the word "Journal," reads in full: "I am now going to write a journal of myself once or twice I indulged a passion which caused me to say I wished my mother was dead. Mr Hyer came to see us and talk to me I can never forget what he said to me he said I ought to give myself to God and I had allready done it I have". On the final page Frances Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's mother, has written: "This journal was begun before we left(?) Fishkill consequently before she was eight years old--it was meant for no eye but her own." See also Post-Mortem Series, item 2.
    - "Story of the Sunday School Children", 1833 January 21; 4.0 pages 16.1 x 39.4 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      A story about five children raised in a "very wicked" household. Four of them are wicked, but the fifth child, Jane, is saved when she learns about God in school. She quotes from the hymn "Little Children, love each other." In Chapter II, Jane's mother send for a man to kill her own children; instead, the man adopts the children into his own happy family, "religious people" who "went to church every Sabbath." At the end, their wicked mother, now "blind and feeble" comes to the children's adopted home but faints "at the sound of their voices." Note in Mary's mother's, (Frances Chrystie's) hand at the bottom of the page reads "Story for the box. Written Between 8 & 9 years of age."
    - "The Hermit's Tale", Undated; 24.9 x 39.3 cm One sheet folded in half; appears to have been bound with other pages at some point. 1 item (Box 1, Folder 12)
      The first four pages of a story by Mary Chrystie entitled "The Hermit's Tale." The epigraph is a quotation from "The Minstrel; or, The Progress of Genius," by James Beattie, who also wrote a poem called "The Hermit" (1771). The plot of this fragment seems to have been influenced by both poems. In the story, a young traveler on a hiking trip hears about a hermit who is supposed to live in the passes of the Blue Ridge Mountains. It contains some lyrical descriptions of landscape: "The night was dark for the moon had not risen but ten thousand times ten thousand little stars were peeping from thier (sic) azure home..." The traveler finds the hermit, "an old man with beard hanging to his waist and long unshorn locks," and tells the hermit about his life. But the story breaks off just as the Hermit begins to tell his own story, a didactic tale "to show how sorrow in age springs from pleasure in youth." The location of the rest of the story is unknown.
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1803-1843; 15.0 items
    Various letters from members of Mary Chrystie's family, mostly written to other family members. Spanning: May 16 1803-March 10 1843. The letters cover these topics of interest: travel in France and Italy, British and American govenments, the War of 1812, Mary's writing ability, family health problems, Mary's death, the birth of William Few Chrystie, Mary Few's and Frances Few's weights, and Mary and William Chrystie's schooling.
    - To William Few, 1816 December 6; 4.0 pages 24 x 39.6 cm On sheet folded in half; Van Der Ley watermark. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      December 6, 1816, Paris; from N. Gallatin, written to her sister Catherine Few, Mary's maternal grandmother, but addressed to Catherine Few's husband Colonel William Few (father of Frances Chrystie, and Mary's grandfather). Gallatin describes English preaching "in the Episcopal Form": "They pray for King George, that he may overcome all of his enemies, that seems so strange to me. But the congreagation are entirely made up of English, nevertheless you may be sure an American cannot relish hearing, or at least cannot unite in offering up such prayers, although they may be very good Christians. The sermons are pretty good but not delivered with much solemnity."; also of note in the letter is a mention of a Frances Gallatin leaving a boarding school after having "not made much progress in speaking French"; and also a mention of an Albert who is visiting Geneva: "He appears to be very happy with his relations and they are fond of him. He says he thinks he must marry there, only they will introduce him to none but old ladies and he reproaches them for it"; also, an interesting postscript: "Vanbrugh Livingston has got quite well and is grown monstrous fat. We see him often."
    - To William, Undated; 4.0 pages 12.2 x 20.3 cm On one piece of notebook paper folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      No date; from "Lily" to William, perhaps Col. William Few, Mary Chrystie's maternal grandfather, but more likely to William Few Chrystie, Mary's brother, or a different William altogether. A brief note in which Lily describes a conversation she had with her mother about the distribution of various pieces of property, such as furniture, a piano, jewelry, and a mirror.
    - To Catherine Few, 1819 April 7; 4.0 pages 22.5 x 36.2 cm One sheet folded in half, with coat of arms watermark. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      April 7, 1819, Paris; from N. Gallatin to her sister, Catherine Few, Mary Chrystie's maternal grandmother. Mrs. Gallatin writes from Paris and sends her letter through the person of a Mr. Bruen, an American preacher; mention is also made of "our poor nephew James Nicholson."
    - To "Smith", 1817 December 13; 4.0 pages 24 x 39 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      December 13, 1817 (with appended entries from 14 and 17 December), New York; from Albert Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's father, to "Smith." A very interesting letter in which Mr. Chrystie writes to his friend Smith who appears to be a member of (or in some way affiliated) with the British Parliament; Mr. Chrystie discusses the relative merits of those in politics and whether their elevation above "us plebians" is just; he reviews the state of politics in Washington and "the high sense we entertain now adays of our own importance as a nation"; he describes his studies, mentions mutual friends, requests a copy of a book ("a handsome edition of Lavater(?)") and describes some orations he has recently seen.
    - To Albert Chrystie, 1814 May 11; 4.0 pages 25.7 x 41.3 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      May 11, 1814, New York: from "L.C."(?) to Albert Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's father. Interesting letter with mention of the War of 1812 and the fighting going on in Europe in 1814, and an optimistic hope for its conclusion: "I am more inclined than ever to think we shall have peace soon--notwithstanding the general Blocade (sic) Yankees & all included!"; remainder of letter discusses friends and family.
    - To Maria, 1803 May 16; 1.0 pages 18.6 x 23.5 cm One sheet with watermark "1800." (Box 1, Folder 13)
      May 16, 1803, New York; from James Nicholson (Mary Chrystie's maternal great-grandfather, and father of Catherine Nicholson Few, Mary's maternal grandmother) to his daughter Maria. Maria is perhaps Mary's great aunt Maria Montgomery. A short letter in which Mr. Nicholson passes on news concerning the family and expresses disappointment that Maria will not be able to be with him as soon as originally expected; Mr. Nicholson patiently accepts the delay: "...yet we submit knowing it is our duty to do so, perhaps as the Alarm of War has taken another turn.'
    - To Matilda Few, Undated; 4.0 pages 25 x 30.7 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      No date; postmarked December 11 at Fishkill Landing; from Frances Few Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's mother, to Matilda Few, Mary Chrystie's aunt. Frances Chrystie writes to her sister who, ten days previously, set off on a journey by sea to Savannah, Georgia; due to strong winds and storms, she expresses no small amount of anxiety over her sister's well-being at sea; she mentions Mary's facility with writing: "...teaching Mary is the greatest possible amusement to me...as to writing I never saw any one learn so fast. She writes whole sentences on the slate without a copy..."
    - To Catherine Few, 1843 March 10; 4.0 pages 24.6 x 38.6 cm One sheet folded in half; paper has some tears and cuts and is almost completely separated along the folded middle seam. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      March 10, 1843, Oak Hills; from J.W. Nicholson, Mary Chrystie's great uncle, to his sisters Catherine Few (Mary's grandmother) and Maria Montgomery (Mary's great aunt). Mr. Nicholson writes to express his condolences over their recent loss (of Mary?); he then goes on to mention the dire illness of his own daughter (named Frances) who suffers from consumption; he mentions his own health problems and complains of being "very weak," a condition he says might be related to his total abstinence from wine and spirits since joining the Temperance Society some months previously--he does, however, acknowledge that his debility could stem from old age.
    - To Catherine Few, 1842 June 15; 4.0 pages 27.5 x 43 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      June 15, 1842, Geneva (date and place taken from note from Frances Chrystie; year taken from postmark); postmarked July 1, 1842 (no place); 2 letters to Catherine Few (Mary Chrystie's grandmother), one from William Few Chrystie (Mary's brother) and one from Frances Few Chrystie (Mary's mother). William consciously avoids writing about the death of his sister Mary and the illness of his father and instead describes his travels for his grandmother in order to "afford...some passing amusement"; Willie has thoroughly enjoyed Italy, preferring Rome should he stay to study, but liking Florence better "for amusement and excitement of every kind"; Venice, "although very striking at first sight soon becomes too monotonous, and the motion of the gondolas although by way of variety still soon becomes exceedingly tiresome"; also described in brief are Milan, a sailing trip around Lake Como, a day spent rowing on Lake Maggiore, an ascent of Simplon Mountain, a visit to Chillon castle and its dungeons (made famous by Lord Byron's "The Prisoner of Chillon"--while there the Chrysties were disappointed in their attempt to introduce themselves to the Countess of Sellon; Frances Chrystie adds a note stating that Albert has recovered from the illness he suffered in Milan, thereby saving her from being "doubly bereaved"; she refers to Mary's death: "...all is not taken from me tho' that which gave me enjoyment in all (sic) is"; she also mentions that they will be returning home via London, and cryptically adds that they may be detained there: "We cannot entirely control our own movements. As soon as we get to L I will let you know why, at present I am bound to secrecy"; she closes by telling her mother that she had a dream in which her Aunt Lizzy(?) appeared to her and told her "All was well," (see also below, item 3 of the "Post-mortem items" series). Frances Chrystie concludes with the following words: "...& so it is dear Mother if Jesus died for us all is well--well for time and well for eternity."
    - To Frances Few Chrystie, 1842 April 23-24; 2.0 pages In the shape of a diamond (labeled 10a), 19.3 x 29.6 cm at widest and longest points. Substantial remains of a black wax seal. One page cut in the shape of a diamond (labeled 10a) used as an envelope for item 10b. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Part 1 of 2; this part of the letter (10a) was folded into an envelope that enclosed the next item (10b).April 23-24, 1842; postmarked May 19, 1842 at Le Havre, France; from Mary Few, Mary Chrystie's aunt, to Frances Few Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's mother. A very densely packed letter--writing covers every available surface--in which Mary Few comforts her sister over the death of Mary Chrystie; in spite of her mind being "obtuse to all that is spiritual," Mary writes to her sister to tell her of various religious sentiments--and pre-sentiments--that she has had; she refers to "how tenderly little Albert Gallatin and she [Mary Chrystie] loved each other in their childhood" and mentions that Albert Gallatin was affected "most keenly" by the news of her death and "was in great danger of falling into his Catholic supersitions" but Mary's "sweet example" might "lure him into the path of truth and holiness"; she refers to a request made by Mary: "Love and remember me, but do not weep for me"; and she comforts Frances Chrystie, reminding her that Mary "chose a better portion even in the full enjoyment of all that this world could bestow--You dedicated her to God--you brought her up for him--He has claimed the free-will offering sooner than you anticipated--He has moved the tender flower--transported it to a more genial clime..."; Mary Few also adds the condolences expressed by many other friends and family members.
    - To Frances Few Chrystie, 1842 April 23-24; 4.0 pages 27.4 x 43.8 cm One sheet folded in half, (labeled 10b), formerly contained in envelope (item 10a). (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Part 2 of 2; this part of the letter (10b) was enclosed inside the previous item (10a). April 23-24, 1842; postmarked May 19, 1842 at Le Havre, France; from Mary Few, Mary Chrystie's aunt, to Frances Few Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's mother. A very densely packed letter--writing covers every available surface--in which Mary Few comforts her sister over the death of Mary Chrystie; in spite of her mind being "obtuse to all that is spiritual," Mary writes to her sister to tell her of various religious sentiments--and pre-sentiments--that she has had; she refers to "how tenderly little Albert Gallatin and she [Mary Chrystie] loved each other in their childhood" and mentions that Albert Gallatin was affected "most keenly" by the news of her death and "was in great danger of falling into his Catholic supersitions" but Mary's "sweet example" might "lure him into the path of truth and holiness"; she refers to a request made by Mary: "Love and remember me, but do not weep for me"; and she comforts Frances Chrystie, reminding her that Mary "chose a better portion even in the full enjoyment of all that this world could bestow--You dedicated her to God--you brought her up for him--He has claimed the free-will offering sooner than you anticipated--He has moved the tender flower--transported it to a more genial clime..."; Mary Few also adds the condolences expressed by many other friends and family members.
    - To Catherine Few, Undated; 4.0 pages 20.4 x 32.9 One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      July 12 (no year), The Rocks; from Mary Few, Mary Chrystie's aunt, to her mother Catherine Few, Mary Chrystie's grandmother. Mary congratulates her mother on becoming a grandmother for the first time (with the birth of William Few Chrystie); Mary is happy that the infant is a boy, "for this world is certainly particularly troublesome to the womankind--and as I always look very far ahead in my calculations I think it particularly fortunate that the eldest is of the protecting sex..."; the rest of the letter mentions many other family members.
    - To Catherine Few, 1835 April 2; 4.0 pages 25.4 x 39.4 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      April 2, 1835, New Haven; postmarked April 3 at New Haven; From Frances Seney(?) to her sister Catherine Few, Mary Chrystie's grandmother. A letter heavily laden with religious sentiment; also mentioned is a revival in religious curiosity and devotion "at the college"--Yale, presumably; Frances also asks her sister about a "Lunitick hospital" that might be able to affect a cure for the son of one of her friends; she also describes a number of profitable lessons she has taken away from her reading of Richerd Baxter's (1615-1691) The Saints' Everlasting Rest (first published in 1650).
    - To Catherine Few, 1804 August 7; 4.0 pages 25.8 x 38.1 cm One sheet folded in half, with watermarks: "W.Y. & Co." and "Gen Stamp Office". 2 different 50 cent stamp(?) images pressed into the paper, one of a bald eagle with shield, the other of a ring surrounding 13 stars. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      August 7, 1804, Windsor Hill; from Mary Few, Mary Chrystie's aunt, to her mother Catherine Few, Mary Chrystie's grandmother. A letter written while visiting the Chrystie family with Frances (not yet married to Albert Chrystie?); Mary notes that she and Frances went to a mill and were weighed; Frances weighed in at 109 pounds, while Mary weighed 100 pounds (see above, item 13 in the "Separately Collected Miscellaneous Letters" series, for Mary Chrystie's own experience of being weighed at a mill.)
    - To Mary Few, Undated; 4.0 pages 24.9 x 39.8 cm One sheet folded in half, with Butler & Ward U.S. watermark. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      September 12 (no year); postmarked September 12 at New York; from Lanny(?)/Fanny(?) to her cousin Mary Few, Mary Chrystie's aunt. Mary's cousin mentions the people she met while on a trip to Albany, including Chancellor Landford, Joe Chartin, Mary Garritson, and Martin van Buren "...whom I was delighted, and quite astonished such an elegant and gentell man should be found in this republican country" (this sighting may date the letter to before 1821 and van Buren's election to the U.S. Senate).
    - To Eliza Durham, 1828 November; 25.4 x 40 cm One sheet folded in half. 1 item (Box 1, Folder 13)
      November 1828; from Frances Few Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's mother, to Eliza Durham, Mary Chrystie's aunt. Mention of Albert Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's father, visiting a prospective school for Willie and Mary (a school on Fulton St.); also mentions a Mr. Stewart who will be serving as chaplain on a "publick vessel" which will take him to the Sandwich Islands; Frances enquires as to how Eliza's school is coming along and whether or not she is making any money with it; a wedding was held at the Chrystie house (the wedding of George Chrystie and Frances Gallatin); Frances Chrystie also mentions that Willie has a "boy doll" that he plays with, and that he informed her that he was going to be a soldier, to which her response was: "I [told him] I thought it would be better to teach him how to be good than to teach him to fight"; little Mary Chrystie's response to Willie's declaration was "Oh Willie you may look at the soldiers but you must worship God"; also, when asked if she has a message for her aunt, Mary says "she has love for you but she won't send it she will give it to you when she goes to Newburgh."
  - Post-mortem Items, 1843; 7.0 items
    Most items are undated, but all were written after Mary Chrystie's death in 1842. Notes from Mary Chrystie's mother, Frances Few Chrystie, and aunt, Mary Few, describing their grief over Mary's death and memorializing her life. The most significant item (item 2) is a hagiography of Mary Chrystie, written by her mother and father. The document is a brief but detailed biography, including many anecdotes that portray Mary as gentle, loving, and pious throughout her short life. The hagiography has been transcribed and a typescript is available in Eric Johnson's notes at Seeley Mudd Manuscript Library.